Semantic Similarity, Engagement Behavior &
Explainable Hashtag Recommendation on TikTok
— NLP Project, IE University 2026
Do TikTok posts with semantically similar captions
form neighborhoods with more homogeneous
engagement profiles?
H₀: Proximity carries no engagement signal.
H₁: Similar content performs more similarly than chance.
→ H₁ holds — uniformly. p ≈ 0.0 across all 12 tests.
26,623 TikTok posts loaded from Supabase (PostgreSQL).
Normalised schema: videos / snapshots / hashtags.
Fields: caption, likes, comments, views, shares.
After cleaning: 22,647 posts retained.
Critical fix: bridge table covered only 3.9% of posts.
Combined extraction → 100% hashtag coverage (5.58 avg/post).
Two-phase pipeline: (1) Extract hashtags → label.
(2) Remove from text → SBERT encodes meaning, not tags.
Emojis: raw Unicode for SBERT | demojized tokens for TF-IDF.
Engagement: log(1+y) transformation.
SBERT (all-MiniLM-L6-v2) encodes each caption
into a 384-dim L2-normalised vector.
cos(u,v) = u·v  after normalisation.
UMAP projects 384-dim embeddings to 2D.
Topical clusters emerge: Fitness / Gaming / Food / Crypto.
Semantic structure is real — not keyword overlap.
FAISS exact cosine KNN index. K ∈ .
Each post's K nearest semantic neighbors retrieved.
(Query post excluded from its own neighborhood.)
σ²_sem(i,K) = Var()
Mann-Whitney U  (alternative='less'):
H₁: σ²_sem < σ²_rand   →   p ≈ 0.0
Reduction% = (1 − σ²_sem̄ / σ²_rand̄) × 100
1,000 random-baseline simulations per K.
4 models, all converge at ~60% accuracy:
• Logistic Regression (SBERT 384-dim)   59% / F1 0.59
• Multinomial Naive Bayes (TF-IDF 10k)  60% / F1 0.58
• KNN k=5 (SBERT)                       59% / F1 0.59
• KNN k=10 (SBERT)                      59% / F1 0.58
→ Information ceiling — not a model failure.
12 Mann-Whitney U tests → p ≈ 0.0 for all.
Variance reduction: 10.5% – 13.0%
H₁ accepted across every metric and every K.
Variance reduction heatmap (%):
likes  comments  views  shares
K= 5:   13.04   12.72   12.32   12.46
K=10:   12.30   12.74   11.36   11.98
K=20:   11.34   11.27   10.46   10.53
→ Monotonic decay: tighter K = stronger coherence.
Input: 'Just hit a new PR at the gym! Hard work pays off 💪'
→ SBERT encode → FAISS KNN → aggregate neighbor hashtags
Recommended: #gymtok · #fitnessforall · #workoutmotivation
Explainable: every tag traces to real similar posts.
Captions don't predict HOW MUCH engagement (~60% ceiling).
But they do predict HOW CONSISTENTLY — 10–13% variance
reduction, p ≈ 0.0, all 12 tests.
The recommender doesn't guess. It learns from posts
that actually mean what yours means.